# UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO SCHOOL OF MEDICINE

# Drew E. Winters, PhD. drew.winters@cuanschutz.edu

# **Biographical sketch**

Drew E. Winters, PhD. is a post-doctoral fellow at the University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus In the department of Psychiatry under the Developmental Psychobiology and Behavior T32 program. His research focuses on brain and behavior mechanisms underlying neurocognitive and socio-affective processes with an emphasis on adolescents with callous-unemotional traits. In this vein, this work aims to identify replicable neural mechanisms that may improve development and testing of interventions for youth with callous-unemotional traits.

# I

interventions for youth with earlous t	anemotional traits.	
Education		
University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, CO Post-Doctoral Fellow: Developmental Psychobiology Research Group (DPRG)		Current
- Primary mentor: Dr. Joseph Sa	akai, M.D.	
Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN.	- Ph.D.	April 2020
Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN.	-MSW	May 2016
Purdue University, Fort Wayne, IN	- B.S.	May 2013
Certifications		
Machine Learning Using Scikit-Learn in Python – Inira		May 2022
Data Scientist in Python - DataCamp		Nov 2021
	Computational Neuroscience – Neuromatch Academy	
Data Scientist in R – DataCamp	•	July 2021 April 2020
Multilevel Modeling II Advanced To	ppics – EITM	Oct 2020
Network Analysis II Advanced Topic		Oct 2020
Structural Equation Modeling with Latent Variables – EITM		Oct 2018
Academic appointments		
University of Colorado	Post-Doctoral Fellow	2020-Present
Indiana University	Adjunct Professor	2017-2020
University of Michigan	Teaching Assistant	2019 & 2020
Indiana University SOM	Research Analyst	2018-2020
Indiana University SOM	Research Assistant	2016-2020
Indiana University	Research Assistant	2014-2015
Hospital, government, or other profession	onal positions	
UCHealth Encompass program - Aur		2020-Present
Family Works Inc Indianapolis, IN		2016-2020
Rogers behavioral health – Skokie IL	•	
Honors, special recognitions, and award	lc	
Postdoctoral Association Travel Awa		2021

# F

Postdoctoral Association Travel Award	2021
University of Colorado, Aurora, CO	
Empirical Implications of Theoretical Models – Statistics Mastery	2021
Multilevel Modeling II: Advanced Topics	

Empirical Implications of Theoretical Mod- Network Analysis II: Advanced Topics	2021		
Empirical Implications of Theoretical Mode Structural Equation Modeling with Later	2018		
Developmental, Child, and Family Psychol ICPSR Quantitative Methods of Social R	2018		
Indiana University Travel Fellow		2017-2019	
Graduate Professional Student Government	Fellowship	2016	
Miranda Pang Endowment	-	2014	
Phi Kappa Phi: Academic Honor Society			
Tau Upsilon Alpha: Human Services Acade	emic Honor Society	2013	
Hellen I. and Rodney E. Nern Scholarship		2013	
Membership in professional organizations			
Society for the Scientific Study of Psychop	athy (SSSP)	2022-current	
Society of Clinical Child and Adolescent P		2020-current	
Society for Social Work and Research (SSV		2017-current	
•			
Major Committee and Service Responsibilitie			
Board of Directors, National Association of	•	2011-2018	
of Abuse Counselors, Indiana Chapter, Indi	anapolis, IN		
Licensure and board certification			
<u>License</u>	<u>Certified</u>	Recertified	
Licensed Social Worker - Colorado	7/2020	7/2021	
Licensed Social Worker – Indiana	7/2016	8/2019	
Review and referee work			
Brain and Behavior	Ad hoc reviewer	2022	
Cerebral Cortex	Ad hoc reviewer	2021	
Psychophysiology	Ad hoc reviewer	2021	
Journal of Drug and Alcohol Dependence	Ad hoc reviewer	2021	
Neuroscience Letters	Ad hoc reviewer	2021	
Journal of Juvenile Justice	Ad hoc reviewer	2018	
Journal of Child and Family Studies	Ad hoc reviewer	2017	
Mindfulness	Ad hoc reviewer	2016	
Invited extramural lectures, presentations and			
Winters, D.E., Sakai, J.T., Carter, R.M., C	-	7/2022	
of Heterogenous Functional Connectomes	•		
Adolescent Callous-Unemotional Traits. No	eurohackadamy,		
University of Washington, Seattle, WA			
Sanchez, C.R., Cooley, J.L., Winters, D.E.	, Ricker, B.T., & Fite, P.J.	7/2022	
Prospective associations between forms of	aggression and peer		
victimization: The moderating role of proso	victimization: The moderating role of prosocial behavior. Biennial		
Research Conference on Relational Aggres			
Winters, D.E., Introduction to R for medical	4/2022		
Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Auro			
Winters, D.E., Cognitive Load Sensitivity In		4/2022	
Impairments in Callous-Unemotional Trait.			
1			

Psychobiology Research Group, Denver, CO		
Winters, D.E., Affective Theory of Mind Impairments in Callous-Unemotional Traits: The Role of Cognitive Co	ontrol.	12/2021
American College of Neuropsychopharmacology. San Winters, D.E., <i>Network typology of adolescents with c unemotional traits</i> . Department of Psychiatry Poster S	allous- ession,	3/2021
University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Av Winters, D.E., Adolescent Prosocial Behavior and Affa Mind: The Role of Cognitive Control and Callousness Developmental Psychobiology Research Group, Denv	ective Theory o	of 3/2021
Winters, D. E., <i>Longitudinal Data Analysis Using Sector</i> S728 multivariate statistics, Dr. Sadaaki Fukui. Indian School of Social Work, Indianapolis, IN.	ondary Data.	1/2021
Winters, D.E., Neural Connectivity of Empathy and its in Adolescents. Developmental Psychobiology Research Denver, CO	-	10/2020
Winters, D.E., <i>Statistical Approaches of Propensity So</i> Training the Indiana Department of Children Services and evaluation team, Indianapolis, IN.		3/2020
Winters, D.E., <i>Secondary data analysis</i> . S728 multiva Dr. Sadaaki Fukui. Indiana University School of Socia Indianapolis, IN.	·	1/2020
Winters, D.E. <i>Mindfulness and Acceptance and Commin Clinical Practice</i> . Advanced clinical practice, Dr. V Starnino, instructor. Indiana University School of Soci Indianapolis, IN.	incent	y 6/2017
Winters, D.E. <i>Mindfulness in Addictions Treatment</i> . Prestaff and clients at the Life Recovery Center, Indianap		8/2016
Winters, D.E. <i>Mindfulness in Clinician Self-Care and Practice</i> . Presented to the staff and honor society recip Eta Sigma for marriage and family therapist. Purdue U Wayne, IN.	ients of Chi	4/2016
Teaching record		
Indiana University School of Social Work – Teaching		C
S623 Practice Research Integrative Seminar	Online	Summer 2017
S623 Practice Research Integrative Seminar S623 Practice Research Integrative Seminar	Online Seminar	Spring 2017 Fall 2016
University of Michigan – ICPSR		
Regression Analysis II: Linear models	Online	Summer 2020
Regression Analysis II: Linear models	Seminar	Summer 2019
Indiana University- Adjunct Professor		
S728 Advanced Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Spring 2020
S718 Intermediate Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Fall 2019
S728 Advanced Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Spring 2019
S718 Intermediate Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Fall 2018

S517 Assessment in Mental Health & Addictions	Seminar	Summer 2018
Mentoring Project Mentor for Neuromatch Academy Computational Neuroscience Track	ıl	2022
- I mentored a group of five participants in the conneuroscience track for Neuromatch Academy or capstone project for the program.		2021
Gabriel Yepes, M.D.  - I mentored Dr. Yepes on conducting research an manuscripts resulting in one research publication	•	2021
Grant support  Developmental Psychobiology Endowment Fund. Project effects of cognitive load on prosocial behavior amongst adolescents with high callous-unemotional traits and type developing controls.' Funding amount \$7,220 Role: PI	early	2021-2022
National Institutes of Mental Health T32MH015442-42; Laudenslager, Mark (PI), Developmental Psychopatholo Psychobiology & Behavior. <u>Role</u> : Postdoctoral Fellow		2020 - present
Indiana Department of Children Services Title IV-E Wa 13-4F-C0-0981; Pierce, Barbra (PI), Indiana University Medicine. Role: Research Analyst		2019 - 2020
Indiana Department of Children Services Title IV-E Wa 13-4F-C0-0981; Hall, Jim (PI), Indiana University School		2017 - 2019

#### **Bibliography**

### **Published**

#### Published Peer-Reviewed Articles

Medicine. Role: Research Assistant

- **Winters, D.E.,** Pruitt P. J., Damoiseaux J.S, Sakai, J.T. (2021). Moderating effect of CU traits on functional connectivity underlying empathy in adolescents. *Psychiatry Research Neuroimaging*. Doi: 10.1016/j.pscychresns.2021.111429
- **Winters D.E.**, Sakai, J.T., Carston, R.M. (2021) Resting-state network topology characterizing callous-unemotional traits in adolescence. Neuroimage: Clinical, 2021: p. 102878.
- **Winters, D.E.,** Susan M., Hopfer, C., Sakai, J.T. (2021). Moderating effects of CU traits on transdiagnostic symptoms association with suicidality in adolescents. *Child Psychiatry and Human Development*. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10578-021-01256-w
- Winters D.E., Pruitt P. J., Fukui S., Cyders M.A., Pierce B. J., Lay K., Damoiseaux J.S. (2021). Indirect paths between functional connectivity underlying heterogenous depression symptoms in adolescents via cognitive and affective empathy. *Child Psychiatry and Human Development*. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10578-021-01242-2
- Winters, D.E., Pruit P.J., Fukui, S., Cyders, M. A., Pierce, B. J., Lay, K., Damoiseaux, J. S. (2021). Network functional connectivity underlying dissociable cognitive and affective components of empathy in adolescence. *Neuropsychologia*. 10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2021.107832
- Winters, D.E., Brandon-Friedman, R., Yepes, G., Hinkley, J. (2020). Systematic review

- and meta-analysis of socio-cognitive and socio-affective processes association with adolescent substance use. *Drug and Alcohol Dependence*. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.108479
- **Winters, D.E.**, Pierce, B. J., Imburgia, T. (2020) Concrete services usage on child placement stability: Propensity score matched effects. *Child and Youth Service Review*. DOI: 10.1016/j.childyouth.2020.105362
- **Winters, D.E.**, Wu, W., Fukui, S. (2020). Longitudinal effects of cognitive and affective empathy on adolescent substance use. *Substance Use & Misuse*, 1-7. DOI: 10.1080/10826084.2020.1717537
- Winters, D.E., Fukui, S., Leibenluft, E., Hulvershorn L.A., (2018). Improvements in Irritability with Open-Label Methylphenidate in Youth with Comorbid Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder and Disruptive Mood Dysregulation Disorder. *Journal of Child and Adolescent Psychopharmacology*, 28(5): 298-305.
- Beerbower, E., **Winters, D.E.**, Kondrat, D. (2018). Bio-psycho-social-spiritual needs of adolescents and young adults with life-threatening illnesses: Implications for social work practice. *Social Work in Health Care*, 1-17. DOI: 10.1080/00981389.2018.1430091
- Winters, D.E., Beerbower, E. (2017). Mindfulness and Meditation as an Adjunctive Treatment for Adolescents Involved in the Juvenile Justice System: Is Repairing the Brain and Nervous System Possible? *Social Work in Health Care*, 1-21. Doi:10.1080/00981389.2017.1316341

### **Published Book Chapters**

Armstrong, E., **Winters, D.E.**, Jaggers, J. (2018). Mental Health in Prison Populations. Serving the Stigmatized: Working within the Incarcerated Environment. W.T. Church and D.W. Springer, Oxford University Press.

# Technical Reports for the State of Indiana

Winters, D.E., Imburgia, T., Pierce, B. J. (2017, 2018, 2019, 2020). Concrete Services Spending and outcomes for youth. Indiana Department of Child Services Child Welfare Title IV-E Waiver Demonstration Project Extension: Final Report.

### Unpublished

#### **Under Review**

- **Winters, D.E.**, Sakai, J.T. (under review). Affective theory of mind impairments underlying callous-unemotional traits and the role of cognitive control: A pilot study.
- **Winters, D.E.**, Massey, S.H., Sakai, J.T. (under review). Adolescent substance use outcomes in response to social consequences of use: the role of empathy.
- Winters, D.E., Sakai, J.T. (under review). Prosocial behavior limitations associated with callous-unemotional traits are moderated by internalizing symptoms
- **Winters, D. E.**, Hyde, L. W. (under review). Shared Functional Network Connectivity Between Callous-Unemotionality and both Cognitive and Affective Empathy.
- Sakai, J.T., Chintaluru, Y., Raymond, K., McWilliams, S., Carter, R., **Winters, D.E.**, Mikulich, S. (under review). Can Moral Elevation Response Increase Prosocial Behavior? Examining the Effects of Psychopathic Traits.

### In preparation

- **Winters, D. E. F**unctional connectivity underlying cognitive control in relation to empathy and callous-unemotional traits.
- Winters, D.E. Callous-Unemotional traits association with prosocial behavior and the

mediating role of cognitive control.